Guide to the Tanka Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Identified Subjects, circa 1600-circa 1950; Series II; (69 paintings)
  - Karmapa Abbots
    - Tanka of a Karmapa Abbot, circa 1800-circa 1950; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 23.0 x 18.5 cm. mounted on silk brocade 48 x 40 cm. (Box 39 (Oversize))
      A watercolor painting on cotton that depicts an unidentified Karmapa abbot wearing a red hat and seated, as well as accompanied by smaller figures of two monks and three protective divinities seated on a horse, elephant, and a mythological creature.
  - Kloṅ-chen-pa Dri-med-'od-zer
    Kloṅ-chen-pa Dri-med-'od-zer (1308-1363), also known as Longchenpa or Longchen Rabjampa, was a major teacher in the Nyingma school of Tibetan Buddhism.
    - Tanka of Kloṅ-chen-pa Dri-med-'od-zer, circa 1700-circa 1800; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 61.0 x 35.5 cm. bordered with silk brocade 118 x 74 cm. (Box 40 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 85.16.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Kloṅ-chen-pa Dri-med-'od-zer or Chos Kyi Rgya Mtsho sitting on a cushion below Amitāyus and two protective divinities and above Vajrapāṇi and dharmapalas.
      Separate inscriptions on verso of painting identify it as Kloṅ-chen-pa Dri-med-'od-zer and Chos Kyi Rgya Mtsho
  - Lobsang Chökyi Gyaltsen
    Lobsang Chökyi Gyaltsen (1570-1662) was the fourth Panchen Lama of Tibet, and the first accorded the title during his lifetime.
    - Tanka of Lobsang Chökyi Gyaltsen, circa 1600-circa 1700; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 64 x 37 cm. bordered with silk brocade 107 x 58 cm. (Box 41 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 85.9.
      A watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Lobsang Chökyi Gyaltsen wearing yellow and seated on cushions with smaller figures of protective divinities, ten lamas, and Güshi Khan (1582-1655), a Khoshut prince and leader of the Khoshut Khanate.
  - Mahākāla
    Mahākāla is a dharmapala in Vajrayana Buddhism.
    - Tanka of Mahākāla, circa 1650-circa 1750; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 44.5 x 34.0 cm. mounted on silk brocade 92 x 58 cm (Box 42 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 85.15.
      A watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Mahākāla with a dark blue body, three heads, and six arms, with ornaments made of human skulls, and accompanied by thirty-eight figures. Consecrated by a lama on the verso with an om-ah-hum and the red hand prints of the lama and the patron.
    - Tanka of Mahākāla, circa 1700-circa 1800; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 39 x 25 cm. bordered with silk brocade 71 x 42 cm. (Box 43 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 85.8.
      A watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Mahākāla with four faces and four arms, with ornaments made of human skulls.
  - Mandalas
    Mandala is a Sanskrit word that means "circle". In Buddhist religious traditions their sacred art often takes a mandala form, which is a square with four gates containing a circle with a center point.
    - Tanka of a Mandala, undated; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 68.5 x 49.0 cm. (Box 44 (Broadside))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.20.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts a mandala consisting of a square with four gates containing a circle with a center point. Miniature figures are depicted outside of the enclosure.
  - Mi-la-ras-pa
    Mi-la-ras-pa (circa 1052-circa 1135), also known as Jetsun Milarepa, was a Tibetan yogi and poet, as well as a founder of the Kagyü school of Tibetan Buddhism.
    - Tanka of Mi-la-ras-pa, circa 1600-circa 1800; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 111 x 68 cm. mounted on bordered with silk 119 x 76 cm. in a frame. (Box 45 (Art))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.6.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Mi-la-ras-pa surrounded by previous hierarchs in the Kagyü school and smaller replicas of himself.
  - Ṅag-dbaṅ-blo-bzaṅ-rgya-mtsho
    Ṅag-dbaṅ-blo-bzaṅ-rgya-mtsho (1617-1682) was the Fifth Dalai Lama and a political and religious leader in seventeenth-century Tibet.
    - Tanka of Ṅag-dbaṅ-blo-bzaṅ-rgya-mtsho, circa 1850-circa 1950; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 65 x 50 cm. bordered with silk 87 x 79 cm. (Box 46 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 59.3.
      A Nepalese watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Ṅag-dbaṅ-blo-bzaṅ-rgya-mtsho, probably in Potala Palace and accompanied by musicians, with other human figures in the foreground.
  - Padma Sambhava
    Padma Sambhava (circa 717-circa 762), also known as Guru Rinpoche or Lopon Rinpoche, was a guru from Oddiyana (modern Swat, Pakistan) credited with introducing Vajrayana Buddhism to Bhutan and Tibet in the eighth century.
    - Tanka of Padma Sambhava, circa 1600-circa 1800; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 37 x 23 cm. bordered with silk 72 x 40 cm. (Box 47 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 85.4.
      A western Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Padma Sambhava seated on a lotus blossom below three smaller protective divinities of Amitābha, Amitāyus, and Tārā, as well as above two smaller figures of Nyingma disciples.
    - Tanka of Padma Sambhava, circa 1850-circa 1950; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 34 x 28 cm. bordered with silk brocade 80 x 61 cm. (Box 48 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 62.1.
      A western Tibetan or Nepalese watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Padma Sambhava with two female consorts, Mandarava and Yeshe Tsogyal.
  - Palden Lhamo
    Palden Lhamo is a female deity who protects the teachings of Gautama Buddha in the Gelug school of Tibetan Buddhism, as well as the principal Protectress of Tibet.
    - Tanka of Palden Lhamo, circa 1600-circa 1700; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 48.0 x 35.5 cm. bordered with silk brocade 74 x 50 cm. (Box 49 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.14.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Palden Lhamo crossing a sea of blood riding side-saddle on a white mule. Above her are Tsoṅ-kha-pa Blo-bzaṅ-grags-pa and a Panchen Lama.
    - Tanka of Palden Lhamo, circa 1600-circa 1700; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 41 x 28 cm. bordered with silk brocade 83 x 55 cm. (Box 50 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.15.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Palden Lhamo crossing a sea of blood riding side-saddle on a white mule. Above her are Tsoṅ-kha-pa Blo-bzaṅ-grags-pa and two of his disciples. Below her is a mounted figure.
    - Tanka of Palden Lhamo, undated; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 59 x 48 cm. in a frame 61 x 51 cm. (Box 51 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 60.3.
      Transferred from the Yale University Art Gallery, 1960. Former Art Gallery No. 1952.40.23.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Palden Lhamo surrounded by miniature figures.
  - Prajñāpāramitā
    Prajñāpāramitā is a concept of buddhist transcendental wisdom perfection is often personified as a bodhisattvadevi (female bodhisattva)
    - Tsakli of Prajñāpāramitā, circa 1700-circa 1800; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 13 x 10 cm. bordered with silk 28 x 26 cm. in a frame. (Box 52 (Oversize))
      An example of a tsakli (also "tsakalis"), a Tibetan miniature painting, normally produced as thematic groups or sets, which are used in rituals. A tsakli can also be placed in a portable shrine or box (Tibetan "gau") and carried as a device giving protection to the traveller or pilgrim who carries this box around the neck or on a shoulder strap.
      Gift of James Robert Tanis (Yale 1951), 1967
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Prajñāpāramitā.
  - Rāhula
    Rāhula is a Tibetan protector deity based on the Indian deity Rahula, an ancient Indian god, a demi-god, of the cosmos, related to the eclipse of the sun, moon and other planets.
    - Tanka of Rāhula, circa 1900-circa 1950; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 56 x 41 cm. bordered with silk brocade 117 x 76 cm. (Box 53 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 81.1.
      Source unknown.
      A Nepalese or Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Rāhula surrounded by eight figures.
  - Rgyan-Tshogs
    Rgyan-tshogs, also known as an assembly of offerings, are pictorial representations of a spectrum of peaceful and wrathful attributes and offerings to the deities.
    - Tanka of a Rgyan-Tshogs, undated; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 49.6 x 37.5 cm., unmounted and unbordered (Box 54 (Broadside))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.22.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts a Rgyan-Tshogs that consists of skulls, bones, flayed human hides, dogs sheep, yaks, and horses.
  - Sa-skya-pa Lama
    The Sa-skya-pa school is one of four major schools of Tibetan Buddhism.
    - Tanka of a Sa-skya-pa Lama, circa 1800-circa 1900; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 60 x 45 cm. bordered with silk brocade 116 x 61 cm. (Box 55 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 85.13.
      An eastern Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts an unidentified Sa-skya-pa lama sitting on a cushion below figures and two guardian divinities and above three protective divinities.
  - Sitātapatrā
    Sitātapatrā is the Goddess of the White Parasol and protector against supernatural danger.
    - Tanka of Sitātapatrā, circa 1800-circa 1900; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 67 x 45 cm. bordered with silk brocade 106 x 73cm. (Box 56 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.9.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Sitātapatrā accompanied by eleven buddha figures above and three deities below.
    - Tanka of Sitātapatrā, undated; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 46.0 x 33.5 cm. bordered with silk 66.5 x 47.5 cm. (Box 57 (Broadside))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.10.
      An unmounted Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Sitātapatrā surrounded by smaller human and other figures.
  - Srid-pa-ho
    A Srid-pa-ho is a Tibetan astrological divinition chart, which includes signs and symbols of the universe.
    - Tanka of a Srid-pa-ho, circa 1900-1950; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 55 x 46 cm. bordered with silk brocade 110 x 79 cm. (Box 58 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.21.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts a Srid-pa-ho. The central figure is a large golden tortoise, representing the Bodhisattva of Knowledge, upon whom are drawn various geomantic diagrams, representing the nine magic squares and symbols of the eight planets.
    - Tanka of a Srid-pa-ho, undated; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 52 x 32 cm., unmounted and unbordered (Box 59 (Broadside))
      Former call number: TIB. 76.5.
      A Tibetan painting of a Srid-pa-ho, which includes a giant golden turtle and twelve animals, as well as Avalokiteśvara, Manjushri, and Vajrapāṇi, known as the Three Family Protectors.
  - Srid-pa'i-'khor-lo
    Srid-pa'i-'khor-lo, also known as bhavacakra or wheel of existence/life, is a symbolic representation of samsāra (or cyclical existence).
    - Tanka of Srid-pa'i-'khor-lo, circa 1800-1900; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 119.5 x 86.5 cm. mounted on silk brocade 176 x 102 cm. (Box 60 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 85.18.
      A Tibetan painting of a Srid-pa'i-'khor-lo held by Yama, also known as Gshin.rje, the prime mover of samsāra, below Gautama Buddha in the upper right corner.
  - Stupa
    A stupa is a dome-shaped monument housing relics of Buddha or an accomplished master.
    - Tanka of a Stupa, circa 1800-circa 1850; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 32.5 x 21.0 cm. bordered with silk 59 x 34 cm. (Box 61 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 76.4.
      A Nepalese or western Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts a stupa.
  - Tārā
    Tārā, also known as Ārya Tārā or Jetsun Dolma, is a female Bodhisattva that represents the virtues of success in work and achievements
    - Tanka of Tārā, circa 1800-circa 1850; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 90.0 x 63.5 cm. bordered with silk brocade 175 x 104 cm. (Box 62 (Art))
      Former call number: TIB. 61.1.
      Gift of Edwin R. Meiss (Yale 1933) and Jean Hoffheimer Meiss, 1961.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Tārā surrounded by 321 miniature replica emanations of herself, as well as two incarnations of the Amitābha and Amitāyus.
    - Tanka of Tārā, circa 1800-1900; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 63 x 44 cm. bordered with silk 94 x 66 cm. (Box 63 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.11
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts a green Tārā surrounded by miniature scenes and figures.
    - Tanka of Tārā, circa 1800-1900; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 79 x 56 cm. bordered with silk brocade 158 x 88 cm (Box 64 (Art))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.12
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts a white Tārā accompanied by four figures above in clouds.
  - Tsoṅ-kha-pa Blo-bzaṅ-grags-pa
    Tsoṅ-kha-pa Blo-bzaṅ-grags-pa (1357-1419), also known as Tsongkhapa, was a teacher of Tibetan Buddhism and founder of the Dge-lugs-pa school of Buddhism, also known as the Yellow Hat sect.
    - Tanka of Tsoṅ-kha-pa Blo-bzaṅ-grags-pa, circa 1650-circa 1750; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 55 x 39 cm. bordered with silk brocade 69 x 86 cm. (Box 65 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 74.1.
      Purchased from Joseph F. Weiler and Eliza Weiler, 1974.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Tsoṅ-kha-pa Blo-bzaṅ-grags-pa accompanied by two disciples.
    - Tanka of Tsoṅ-kha-pa Blo-bzaṅ-grags-pa, circa 1650-circa 1750; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 68 x 48 cm. bordered with silk brocade 139 x 73 cm. (Box 66 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 66.3.
      Purchased in New Delhi, India, by Wesley E. Needham, 1966.
    - Tanka of Tsoṅ-kha-pa Blo-bzaṅ-grags-pa, circa 1700-circa 1800; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 51.0 x 35.5 cm. in a frame 54 x 38 cm. (Box 67 (Box))
      Former call number: TIB. 60.2.
      Transferred from the Yale University Art Gallery, 1960. Former Art Gallery No. 1952.40.22.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Tsoṅ-kha-pa Blo-bzaṅ-grags-pa surrounded by miniature figures.
  - Vajrabhairava
    Vajrabhairava, also known as Yamāntaka, a wrathful manifestation of Mañjuśrī, the bodhisattva of wisdom, and in other contexts functions as a dharmapala, or 'Dharma-protector'.
    - Tanka of Vajrabhairava, circa 1700-circa 1800; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 60.5 x 41.0 cm. bordered and mounted on silk brocade 117 x 73 cm. (Box 68 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 85.17.
      A central Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Vajrabhairava with a dark blue body, nine heads, thirty-four arms, and sixteen legs, as well as wearing a garland of fifty human heads. He is below smaller figures, including Atiśa Dipankara Shrijnana (980-1054), also known as Atisha, a Buddhist teacher from the Pala Empire, and Tsoṅ-kha-pa Blo-bzaṅ-grags-pa with two disciples, as well as two protective divinities. He is above smaller figures of divinities, including Begtse, Yama, Yami, and Lha-mo.
  - Vajrapāṇi
    Vajrapāṇi is a Buddhist bodhisattva and the protector and guide of Gautama Buddha.
    - Tanka of Vajrapāṇi, circa 1800-circa 1900; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 46.5 x 33.5 cm. bordered with silk brocade 88 x 61 cm. (Box 69 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.13
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Vajrapāṇi, and includes three miniature horse heads and a garuda holding a serpant above his crown.
    - Tanka of Vajrapāṇi, circa 1900-circa 1950; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 66 x 52 cm. bordered with silk 104 x 76 cm. (Box 70 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 59.5.
      A western Tibetan or Nepalese watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Vajrapāṇi surrounded by eight figures.
  - Vajrasattva
    Vajrasattva is a bodhisattva associated with the Dharmakaya and with purification practice.
    - Tanka of Vajrasattva, circa 1600-circa 1800; 1 needlework: silk on silk; 100 x 73 cm. bordered with silk 135 x 103 cm. (Box 71 (Art))
      Former call number: TIB. 73.1.
      Gift of Mr. and Mrs. John Roger, 1973.
      A central Tibetan silk appliqué on silk that depicts Vajrasattva seated on a lotus throne holding a vajra (dorje) and ghanta (bell). The mountains were likely added later by a Korean or Japanese artist.
    - Tanka of Vajrasattva, circa 1600-circa 1800; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 51 x 36 cm. bordered with silk 108 x 72 cm. (Box 72 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 85.6.
      A Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Vajrasattva seated on a lotus holding a vajra (dorje) and ghanta (bell), below three smaller figures: a lama, Adi-Buddha, and Atiśa Dipankara Shrijnana, as well as above three protective divinities: Palden Lhamo, Mahākāla, and Yama.
  - Vajrayoginī
    Vajrayoginī is the Vajra yoginī, literally 'the diamond female yogi'. Her practice includes methods for preventing ordinary death, intermediate state (bardo) and rebirth (by transforming them into paths to enlightenment), and for transforming all mundane daily experiences into higher spiritual paths.
    - Tanka of Vajrayoginī, circa 1700-circa 1900; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 61 x 38 cm. bordered with silk 90 x 55 cm. (Box 73 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.17.
      A western Tibetan or Nepalese watercolor painting on cotton that depicts a red Vajrayoginī drinking blood from a human skull and surrounded by many miniature figures.
    - Tanka of Vajrayoginī, undated; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 54 x 36 cm. bordered with silk brocade 63.5 x 44.5 cm. (Box 74 (Broadside))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.18.
      An unfinished Tibetan watercolor painting on cotton that depicts a red Vajrayoginī wearing a necklace skulls and drinking blood from a human skull. She is also surrounded by many miniature figures.
  - Vasudhārā
    Vasudhārā is the Buddhist bodhisattva of wealth, prosperity, and abundance.
    - Tanka of Vasudhārā, circa 1870-circa 1900; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 65.0 x 42.5 cm. bordered with silk 117 x 90 cm. (Box 75 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 59.4.
      A Nepalese watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Vasudhārā accompanied by smaller male and female divinities. The painting includes decorative elements to mimic silk brocade.
  - Viśrāvaṇa
    Viśrāvaṇa, also known as also known as Jambhala or the King of the North, is a worldly dharmapāla or protector of the Dharma and a god of wealth.
    - Tanka of Viśrāvaṇa, circa 1900-circa 1950; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 89.5 x 58.0 cm. bordered with silk 137 x 82 cm (Box 76 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 68.2.
      Gift of Wendell Phillips Colton, Jr. (Yale 1929) and Cornelia Mary Safford Colton, 1968.
      A Nepalese watercolor painting on cotton that depicts Viśrāvaṇa on a white horse with smaller figures on elephants, a lion, and a tiger in the four corners.
  - Yungtön Dorjepel
    Yungtön Dorjepel (1284-1365), also known as Gyun-ston-rdo-rje-dpal, was considered to be the final Tibetan incarnation of Amitābha Buddha before Khedrup Gelek Pelzang (1385-1438), who is recognized as the First Panchen Lama.
    - Tanka of Yungtön Dorjepel, circa 1700-circa 1800; 1 painting: watercolor on cotton; 71 x 47 cm. framed with silk 124 x 68 cm. (Box 77 (Oversize))
      Former call number: TIB. 67.7.
      A Tibetan painting of Yungtön Dorjepel wearing a red hat, with smaller figures of his teacher, three disciples and divinities.